<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright (C) Minimax Labs Ltd., 2010 - 2016
    All rights reserved.

-->
<chapter xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<title>Application Overview</title>

	<para>LiNGO is an LNG portfolio optimisation and management software product. Featuring a rich, highly functional user interface (UI) and it enables business
		users to:
	</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Model vessels, ports, cargoes, contracts,  etc. data and constraints in detail</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Evaluate complex contract and corporate P&amp;L logic</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Optimise ship scheduling and portfolio configuration (specifically, buy-sell pairs) to maximise post-tax group P&amp;L.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Discover and exploit opportunities in both cargo and shipping markets.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Manage operations and analyse risk.</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>It is often highly customised, particularly around contract and entity P&amp;L logic, reporting and systems integration.</para>
	<para>LiNGO is based around Scenarios, a collection of data which completely defines a snapshot of the portfolio (cargoes, shipping, contracts, entities, as
		well as reference data for ports, vessels, port and canal costs, etc.). Scenarios are the self-contained data files and can largely be thought of as
		traditional files.
	</para>
	<para>Users edit scenarios to reflect current business and operational conditions evaluate possible trading and shipping decisions. Built-in auto-validation
		checks all physical and commercial constraints and highlight violation to the user for correction.
	</para>
	<para>We give here an overview of the application just as a user sees it. Other sections of this guide will focus on data model, common use
		cases and
		questions.
	</para>
	<para>Firstly a note on the structure of the application, then descriptions of each part of the main Analysis screen (perspective), then followed by Reports
		and the Data perspective.
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>
			Screens (aka Perspectives) and windows (aka Views)
		</title>
		<para>
			A view is a window which generally displays some data or diagram (such as the editing view. LiNGO has a number or carefully configured screens or
			Perspectives, which group together Views within a common context. For example, Analysis (illustrated) covers portfolio modelling and optimisation while Data
			contains and handles editing of all the reference data.
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/overview.png" width="100%" />
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Icons</title>
		<para>Many Views have small icons in the top right corner providing commonly-used commands:</para>
		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*" />
				<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="7*" />
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/icons-add.png" width="1.236cm" depth="0.601cm" />
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Add
						</entry>
						<entry>Add an existing vessel to the fleet or create a new “Charter Out”, “Maintenance” or “Dry Dock” vessel event.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/icons-delete.png" width="0.601cm" depth="0.601cm" />
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Delete
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Delete the selected rows.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/icons-pack-columns.png" width="0.742cm" depth="0.601cm" />
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Pack Columns
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Resize table columns to fit data
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/icons-filter.png" width="1.095cm" depth="0.636cm" />
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Filter
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Filter data based on specified names or other fields.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/icons-copy-to-clipboard.png" width="0.671cm" depth="0.636cm" />
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Copy to Clipboard
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Copy data in Excel compatible format to the clipboard.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</section>
	<section id="View_Navigator">
	<?dbeclipse ctx_title="About the Scenario Navigator" ?>
		<title>Scenario Navigator</title>
		<para>The Scenarios Navigator is common to all perspectives and drives most use of the application. Here, the user manages the scenarios in the workspace and
			selects them for viewing, editing and optimising.
		</para>
		<para>
			The scenarios are organised into a tree of repositories
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/ScenarioService.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			, folders
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/Folder.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			and scenarios
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/ScenarioInstance.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			. A folder is just like a directory on the filesystem, containing other folders and scenarios. Folders are stored on the local machine and optionally on a
			network share. The repositories, “My Scenarios” and “Base cases (shared)”, are hidden if the share is not enabled.
		</para>
		<para>
			The Pin
			<inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-pin.png" depth="0.4cm" />
				</imageobject>
			</inlinemediaobject>
			and Display
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-display.png" />
			icons control how scenarios appear in comparative reports. Pinning a scenario selects it as the base case to compare other scenarios
			against in comparative
			reports. Only one scenario may be pinned at one time. The pinned scenario is always featured in a comparative
			report. The Display icon determines whether a
			scenario is shown in a
			comparative report: if it is selected
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-display.png" width="0.477cm" depth="0.451cm" />
			, the scenario will be displayed, while if it is unselected
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-display-grey.png" width="0.371cm" depth="0.398cm" />
			then the scenario will not appear on comparative reports. Clicking on a Display icon will toggle it between selected and unselected.
			Double-clicking on a
			Display icon will pin the scenario.
		</para>

		<informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/views-scenario-navigator.png" width="6cm" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalfigure>

		<para>
			The
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/bg-eval.png" width="0.53cm" depth="0.504cm" />
			column in the Scenarios View shows when work (evaluation or
			optimisation) is being done by the application on a scenario, so
			that
			the scenario is not available
			for editing. A scenario
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/ScenarioInstance.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			may also be overlaid with icons showing it has validation warnings
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-warning.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			and errors
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-error.gif" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			, is locked for editing
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-lock.png" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
			or is being optimised
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-opt.png" width="0.186cm" depth="0.213cm" />
			.
		</para>
		<para>Scenarios and folders can be moved around by drag and drop
			(hold
			down control to copy rather than move). The usual copy
			(CTRL+C) and
			paste (CTRL+V) actions
			can be used both within the
			Navigator and to
			transfer scenarios to and from the Windows
			filesystem or Desktop
			(where they have the “.lingo” file
			extension).
		</para>
		<para>
			Double-clicking on a scenario will open it in the scenario editor.
			Single click on a scenario to snap the editor and display to that
			scenario (if open).
		</para>
		<para>Scenarios can be “forked”. Forking simply creates a copy of
			the scenario, displayed under the contained under the parent scenario.
			Note: a scenario can
			only be placed under another scenario as a result of a fork.
		</para>

		<informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/context-menu.png" width="7.259cm" depth="7.21cm" />
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para>Tip: Use forking to make chain of scenarios to track an
						evolving analysis case.
					</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalfigure>


		<para>Right-clicking on a scenario or folder will open the context
			menu:
		</para>
		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4*" />
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Go Into</entry>
						<entry>
							Change the focus of the scenarios view to the selected folder.
							This can be adjusted by clicking the back
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-back.png" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
							, forward
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-forward.png" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
							or up
							<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/scenario-navigator/nav-up.png" width="0.424cm" depth="0.424cm" />
							icons.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>New Folder</entry>
						<entry>If a folder is selected, create a new folder inside it.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Rename</entry>
						<entry>Rename a scenario or folder.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Copy</entry>
						<entry>Copy a scenario or folder, to paste into Scenario Navigator or a Windows folder.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Paste</entry>
						<entry>Paste a scenario from LiNGO or a Windows folder.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Delete</entry>
						<entry>Delete a scenario. This action cannot be undone.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Revert</entry>
						<entry>If you have made any unsaved changes to a scenario, abandon those changes and go back to the last saved version.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Fork</entry>
						<entry>Make a new version of a scenario for quick editing and comparison.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Optimise</entry>
						<entry>Attempt to automatically optimise the scenario, producing a commercially improved schedule by changing the allocation of trades and vessels, as
							well as some other factors.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Fork and Optimise</entry>
						<entry>Fork a scenario and then optimise the fork.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Pin / Unpin</entry>
						<entry>“Pin” or “unpin” the scenario. A pinned scenario is used as the base for comparison in comparative reports.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Export Scenario as CSV</entry>
						<entry>Save the scenario in CSV format, allowing the scenario data to be edited in Excel or another spreadsheet.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</section>
	<section id="View_Validation">
		<title>Validation</title>
		<para>The Validation view displays a list of warning and error
			messages for the scenario currently being edited.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note: not to be confused with application errors recorded in the
			Error Log view.
		</para>
		<informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="resources/overview/validation view.png" />
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para>Tip: Double-click on a validation message to switch to and
						highlight the relevant data item in the relevant editor tab (note for
						ports and vessels,
						etc.
						switch to the Data perspective).
					</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalfigure>

		<para>Warning messages are generally data issues which the optimiser
			can work around but may lead to suboptimal results. Error messages
			are generally for gaps
			or inconsistencies in the input data, or
			conflicting requirements that the optimiser is unable to fix (by
			moving slots around), or even evaluate properly.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="View_ErrorLog">
		<title>Error Log</title>
		<para>
			The Error Log view records internal application errors (not to be
			confused with scenario data errors, shown in the Validation view).
			This view provides
			invaluable information for debugging problems so
			any bug report should provide a copy of the Error Log together with
			related scenarios and steps to reproduce.
			Export the Error Log
			using
			the "Export Log”
			<inlinegraphic fileref="resources/overview/export error log.png" width="0.53cm" depth="0.504cm" />
			button.
		</para>
		<informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="resources/overview/error log.png" width="11.749cm" depth="4.949cm" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalfigure>
	</section>
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="menubar.xml" />
</chapter>